hello this is Frankie Freitas and
welcome to the first broadcast of
holotalk
a weekly show that we're putting
together to let you in on what's
happening in the world of holography we
have a toll-free number now where you
can call in with your questions which we
would be happy to answer here on the
show that toll-free number is across the
U.S
1-800-458-3525 and if you're outside of
the U.S you can dial area code
610-770-0341 and leave your questions on
the machine and we'll bring them into
the show we'd like to use your voice but
it's not necessary for you to leave your
name or where you're calling from but
we'd like to have your question on the
show if you'd like to use email that's
fine too we get a lot of questions
through email all the time and we're
going to start answering them on this
program the email address is holotalk
holoworld.com so send your questions in
we're planning on having some guests
with us as well as time goes on so we
can talk to some people that are
actually work working in the field of
holography
and if you have a question for any
specific field we'll let you know what's
coming up the following week and you can
send your questions in at that point
let's get to a couple of the questions
that we had come in recently you know
this is a question that's been coming in
quite a bit this time of year and uh
also through the years as I've had the
holography studio through regular mail
and since I've had the internet webzema
photography on the web through email and
that question is what would you
recommend for a junior high school or
high school science fair project with
hologography and lasers
my answer to that is and listen to this
carefully my answer to that is if you
already have a small holography lab in
your science department at either your
junior high school or your high school
go for doing a hologram and putting that
in the science fair project and writing
up about it it's an excellent choice
it's always a very high score with
science fair projects across the country
however
if you do not already have the
facilities to make a hologram and by
facilities this is what I mean you're
going to need some sort of isolation
system which dampens the vibration now
this can either be a small table that
you put together yourself using the
little neoprene balls that they sell now
that you can rest a surface on and do
the Holograms they're very easy easy to
create or building a sand table which
sometimes is a a real pain to to put
that up and have to take it down just
for science fair project
uh most science departments at junior
high schools and high schools that
already have a laser have a very low
power laser you're not going to find a
35 milliwatt laser sitting in a high
school somewhere at least I don't think
you are I haven't seen any 35 millim
watt lasers out there
what you're going to find are half
milliwatt helium neon lasers
and to be quite Frank with you I do not
think that you have enough power with a
half milliwatt laser to do anything
that's going to impress judges at a
science fair can you make a hologram
with a half milliwatt laser sure I've
seen them done they're small Holograms
maybe on those little glass plates that
you can buy that are two and a half by
two and a half inches when you cut up a
larger piece of film like a four by five
inch sheet into a smaller piece
but you're not going to get anything
that's going to knock anybody's socks
off when they come around to your table
to see what it is that you've done
what I recommend people do is if you
have a laser already
in your science department you want to
do a project
unless you've got the facilities to make
a hologram stay away from holography go
instead to doing a specific project
using just the laser which is much
easier and you can use a half milliwatt
laser here are some of the things that I
recommend number one this is a quite
popular one and this answers the
question this is this would be the
question of your science fair project
does laser light change the size or
shape of an object and here's what we
normally do we take an object a simple
object like a wooden block or something
else that can be measured quite easily
and we illuminate that object with white
light and the shadow gets cast onto
graph paper we then Mark on that graph
paper the size of the shadow that the
object makes
then we take the helium neon laser and
we pass that beam through a lens and we
illuminate the object one more time this
time using the laser light we keep our
graph paper in the same spot so that
we're not changing anything with the
setup except for the light source itself
and then once that object is illuminated
with the laser light and is casting a
shadow onto the graph paper then we take
our measurement again
we see does laser light change the size
or shape of an object and then you have
to go on to give your reasons why is it
really because it's a different light
source than the white light source that
we used or does the lens have anything
to do with it the fact that we're taking
that unspread bean and spreading it out
and then casting the Shadow with the
diverging beam this is a very popular
science fair project and there's a
number of other ones too that for
instance lasers are being used in
industry and construction so you may be
able to show
um a pipe you can take a laser beam and
send it through a pipe and show if the
pipe is actually bent in any in any
areas and things of that nature from the
laser being passing through on the other
side so there's there's a number of
things that you can do that you already
have right in your science department
and the only additional items you would
need
especially for the first item that I
mentioned would be a diverging lens
which would take a laser beam and spread
it out
so that's my answer on that question if
you've got a science fair project coming
up in a nutshell if you have equipment
already to do holography which is a
little bit of an isolation system you're
going to have to have lenses and these
lenses should be in pretty good shape
this can't be the same type of lens it's
being passed around to 40 kids in the
class and they've got their fingerprints
all over it and things of that nature
these need to be pretty good lenses to
do a good hologram you're going to need
front surface mirrors you can't use
mirrors that have the silver on the back
because you're going to get a very
strong interference pattern once that
beam is reflected off that mirror and
then pass through a lens you're going to
notice a lot of fringes you have to have
a front surface mirror and once again it
should be in very good shape so if you
don't already have these items my
suggestion to you would be just go with
the laser that you have and do a simple
project answering a few questions about
laser light itself
okay let's move on to our next question
by the way if you have a question that
you'd like to send into the show we'd
love to put it on the air
the toll-free number across the U.S is
1-800-458-3525 leave your question on
the answering machine you don't need to
leave your name or the area that you're
calling from just leave your question
we'd love to hear your voice on the show
you can also send email to holotalk at
holoworld.com
we got a question and this is a common
question as well just like the first one
how much power do I need in a laser to
make a hologram and that's a good
question number one
power equals dollars how how much money
do you have to spend that that would
have to be the first thing that I would
have to ask you a half milliwatt laser I
would try and stay away from it if
possible because number one you will be
able to do very small Holograms I don't
know if you'd be able to move into a
split being set up but you'd be able to
make single beam Holograms with the half
mil opportunity they're going to be very
small Holograms and there's no room for
growth now what if you find out that you
really like holography and you'd like to
stick with it what are you going to do
you can't move up to bigger Holograms
because you don't have the power to do
it
when I first got started in holography I
made the initial investment to buy a
five milliwatt laser and I made sure
that it was polarized too and that's
very important although you can do
Holograms without a polarized laser you
don't need one to be polarized to make
Holograms but if you have a polarized
beam you're going to find out that
you're going to
you're going to save a lot of power as
that being travels through your Optical
system you'll find out that with a
polarized laser the beam will travel
through the lens with less reflection
coming off of that substrate than if you
were to have a non-polarized laser so
why spend the money for a five millilit
unpolarized laser when you're going to
be losing a lot of that power as it
travels around the table and going
through different lenses
so get yourself a five milliwatt laser
make sure that it's polarized I have
done in the past back in the mid 80s I
did multiple color Holograms four by
five inch glass plate Holograms using a
five milliwatt laser utilizing the
triathanolamine technique which is uh
pre-swelling the plate pretty swelling
the Emulsion actually before you do the
exposure for each of the individual
colors so not only will you be able to
start out and learn holography and do
your very simple Holograms with a five
milliwatt laser But as time goes on and
you want a little bit more of a
challenge in your holographic Journey a
five milliwatt laser is going to give
you enough room for growth that you can
start moving into some very interesting
projects with holography so go with the
five milliwatt if you can if you can I
know there are a number of different
three milliwatts out there it might be a
nice middle of the road but if I were
you I would stay away from the half
milliwatt lasers they're just not worth
the the money that you're going to put
out you're going to be disappointed
after a while when you just can't move
on
okay let's move on to our third question
this is an interesting question I get I
get this an email every so often I don't
get it a lot but every so often and that
question is I need information on
Holograms that float in space
now I'm not quite sure what the person
is asking about here but my guess is
that they're asking about holographic
images that just sort of like hang in
space and float in front of you
and unless I haven't seen it I do not
know of any holographic images that just
sort of like hover in space I know
there's a number of different techniques
that can be used there are lasers that
can draw three-dimensional images inside
of crystals there are also ways of
projecting images out in space using
conventional Optics such as collimating
mirrors
and this this is the type of technique
that's used down in the haunted house
that everyone always comes up to me and
asks me oh I saw the holographic faces
in the haunted house ride down in in
Disney World in Florida I've not been
there myself I do not know firsthand
what this looks like when people are
seeing it but they're thinking that it's
a hologram from my research looking into
this I found out that Disney uses
traditional Optical techniques to do
that and it's either a slide or some
sort of transparency or a moving image
such as a a videotape or film that's re
that's reflected off a collimating
mirror now what collimating mirror does
is it will take that light and it will
focus it out in space
but keep in mind that this is not a
three-dimensional image just because
it's floating in space if you were to
stop in your tracks and really examine
this image you'd find out that even
though it's hovering there in front of
you and you probably reach out with your
hand and pass your hand through it the
actual image itself is flat it's not
three-dimensional if it were someone's
face
the nose would not be closer to you than
one of the ears it would all be on the
same plane and just because it's
floating in space does not necessarily
make it a hologram myself I have never
seen a holographic image that was just
hovering in space to Additionally you
need either a holographic plate to store
the information on with a light
sensitive Emulsion which contains The
Fringe patterns or you need the film
which does the same thing now with the
stereograms there's 180 degree
stereograms and there's 360 degree
stereograms you've seen these they're
fairly popular I like them quite a bit
they're originally shot on Motion
Picture film and as the cylinder turns
it's usually on a little motor and it
has a light at the base that comes up
and illuminates the inside of the
Hologram and the image is focused to the
center of that cylinder which makes it
appear to float in space in between the
um in in between the walls of the
cylinder as that cylinder rotates
that's probably as close as you're going
to get to seeing an image actually hover
in space and of course that's hovering
inside a a device not outside in thin
air so
my answer to this and correct me if I'm
wrong you can also call and correct me
anytime that you want to or send an
email that's fine I do not know of any
Holograms
that you can sit down and just see that
object or person or whatever the
Hologram is made of just hover in space
in front of you unless there's something
to do with a film or plate that has that
holographic information on and there's a
light that's shining on that hologram
that's taking the light and actually
projecting it out so
I don't know what information to give
you on Holograms that float in space but
I would have a tendency to tell you to
look into other techniques it's not a
holographic technique at all
okay so we're going to wrap up this
first broadcast of hello talk I'd like
to thank you for listening if you have
any questions regarding lasers and or
Holograms that you'd like to see covered
here and answered on holotalk I'd like
to remind you once again we do have a
toll-free number across the U.S that
number is
[Music]
1-800-458-3525 you can leave your
message on the answering machine that
will take your call and you do not need
to leave your name or the area that
you're calling from but we would really
like to use your voice actually asking
the question on the air with upcoming
shows If you prefer you can also use
email you can send your questions to
holotalk at
holoworld.com and we will get your
questions on the air that way as well
I'd also like to remind you that we are
planning on having guests on the show
which we will do a short interview with
people who are working in the field of
Photography and please tune in for
future shows to see what's coming up as
far as guests are concerned so this is
Frank defray this for holo talk thank
you for tuning in and I look forward to
having you listen to the show again next
week here at the internet webcam of
holography good night
but